(upbeat music)
- Hello everyone and
welcome to English Pod.
My name is Marco.
- My name is Catherine and
today we have a lesson for you
all about life at home
and life with your parents.
- That's right, we've all
lived with our parents
when we were younger
or maybe we still do.
And of course, they have
certain rules in the house
and well, when you break those rules,
something happens, there are consequences
and that's what's happening
in today's dialogue.
- So let's take a listen to this dialogue
and when we come
back, we'll be talking more
about what's going on and what
some of these words and phrases mean.
(upbeat music)
- Do you know what time it is?
- 10.
- Get in this door
young man, it's midnight.
You are two hours past curfew.
- I know, but it wasn't my fault.
I told Jennifer she had to drop me off
before 10, but she wouldn't leave the party.
- I don't care, you are
grounded for life, Mr.
- Mom, that is so unfair.
- You know the rules and you broke them.
No allowance and no TV for a week.
I usually never ground you, but
this time I have to put my foot down.
- What?
For being a couple of hours
late, you have to be kidding.
- I don't wanna hear
it, now go to your room.
(upbeat music)
- All right, we're back,
so a very typical case.
Somebody or the kid returns home,
it's too late, and now they're in trouble.
- Yes, his parents are not
very happy, in this case it's
his mom who is telling him
what the consequences will be.
So let's take a look at language takeaway
and find out what some
of these keywords are.
- Language takeaway.
- All right, so the first
word that we're gonna
take a look is actually
something that his mom said,
and he said that you
are two hours past curfew.
- Curf you, so curfew
has to do specifically
with the time when your
parents expect you at home.
- That's right, so if
your curfew is 10 o'clock,
you have to be home
before or by 10 o'clock.
- Right, so in this case, if
the boy's curfew is 10 o'clock
and he arrives home at midnight
12 o'clock, he's two hours past curfew.
- That's right, and even
sometimes cities or governments
will implement certain
curfews at certain times.
- That's right, and I
don't think adults really
have curfews at home, it
depends on what you want.
But kids definitely have curfews.
What happens though,
Marco, when you break curfew?
- So this is a very serious offense
and you're gonna get punished.
And the way that we say
this, usually parents to their
children, you are grounded
or you ground that kid.
- Okay, so you might have heard this word
when talking about airplanes
or flights at an airport.
The plane was grounded.
It basically means it can't go anywhere.
And so when you're
talking about a kid or a
person, you basically
mean, okay, you're grounded,
you can't go out with your
friends, you can't go anywhere.
Usually you can go to school, but
you can't have fun is the meaning.
- That's right, so it's
usually a fixed phrase,
you're grounded, that means that
you are punished, you can't go out.
But in this case, the mom
specified saying you're
grounded, so that means
that he can't go out.
But on top of that, she said no
allowance and no TV for a week.
- Man, so allowance is the
money that your parents give you
to go out, like to go to
the movies or something.
And your parents might
give this to you on a weekly
basis, so every Saturday
you get five dollars,
or on a monthly basis,
every month you get $20.
And when his mother says you're
not gonna have any allowance
for a week, that means we're not
gonna give you any money this week.
- That's right, so that is an allowance,
how much money you
get per month or per week.
The key thing about
allowance, though, is that it's not
something you do for work, you
don't work and receive allowance.
If you work, you have a salary,
allowance is something that
you get for free from someone.
So you can get an allowance
from your boss to eat,
but you can also have an allowance
for your parents to do fun things.
- That's right, so usually
kids, obviously, they can't work,
so they get an allowance
from their parents,
usually for fun things, like
going to the movies and stuff.
- Exactly.
- All right, now, going back a little bit,
let's take a look at two
ways that the mom addressed
or called her son, because
obviously it's her son.
But when he got home, she
said, "Get in this door, young man.
" - Okay, these are
angry mom phrases.
(laughs)
When you're in trouble, your parents
tend to use different words to talk to you.
So this is a very popular one, young man.
So it's like saying, you should be
mature, but you made a mistake.
- Yeah.
- All right, so come inside
right now, young man.
- Yeah, it's a way to kind of
emphasize that you are also very angry.
And also, when he was trying
to explain what happened,
she said, "I don't care,
you're grounded for life, Mr.
" - You're
grounded for life, Mr.
So these are both ways
of talking to young boys.
Mr. is the opposite of miss.
But in the case of a young girl,
you'd say, "Get in this door, young lady.
" - Right.
- And then you're grounded for life, missy.
- Missy.
- Yeah, I think they say missy.
- Missy, so missy,
Mr. young man, young lady.
These are always referring
to people in kind of,
it's weird, it's kind of like
their adults, but they're not.
- Yeah, that's right.
- That's like saying, you're in trouble.
- Yeah.
So very interesting things going on here
with this young man who got grounded.
Why don't we go
back, let's take a look at
her dialogue again
and we'll be back in a bit.
(upbeat music)
(tense music)
- Do you know what time it is?
- 10.
- Get in this door, young man.
It's midnight.
You are two hours past curfew.
- I know, but it wasn't my fault.
I told Jennifer, she had to drop me off
before 10, but she wouldn't leave the party.
- I don't care.
- You are grounded for life, Mr.
- Mom, that is so unfair.
- You know the rules and you broke them.
No allowance and no TV for a week.
I usually never ground you, but
this time I have to put my foot down.
- What?
For being a couple of hours
late, you have to be kidding.
- I don't wanna hear it.
Now go to your room.
- All right, we're back.
So now let's take a
look at four key phrases
that we've picked out
for you on Fluency Builder.
- Fluency Builder.
All right, so this first
phrase is something
that actually we hear
when the young boy or the
young man is giving
his excuse for being late.
He said, listen, I told Jennifer,
she had to drop me off before 10.
- That's right.
So the phrasal verb there is to drop off.
- This means to leave someone somewhere.
- That's right.
- But usually it means to drive
someone to a certain place.
So for example, Jennifer probably has a car
and Jennifer was supposed
to take this boy home.
So he said, she was going to
drop me off before 10 o'clock.
That means kind of leave him at his house.
- That's right.
So the verb is to drop off, but we
usually insert the subject in between it.
So to drop me off, she
is going to drop me off.
- I dropped him off at the bank.
- That's right.
All right, so now that
Jennifer was supposed
to drop him off at
10, that didn't happen.
So he got grounded and his mom was saying
that she usually doesn't really ground him,
but this time I have to put my foot down.
- She's angry.
- Yeah.
- He's upset and she's angry and she
said listen, I have to put my foot down.
Well, what does this mean?
You put your foot on the ground.
It's strange to hear this phrase, huh?
- It means that she's going to be strict.
That she's not going to let him just
get away with it or not ground him.
She really has to be strict
and she has to punish him.
- Okay, so to put your foot down
or I put my foot down, this
means to be strict with someone,
it's not maybe bend
the rules or be flexible.
So for example, my mother
was always very, very loose
with my brother, he could do
what he wanted or whatever,
but one day he did something really
horrible and she finally put her foot down.
- And she grounded him.
- She grounded him for three months.
All right, so that's what
happens when somebody puts
their foot down and now
obviously he was very surprised
that he's going to be grounded for so long
and only for being a couple of hours late.
So he said, you have to be kidding.
- You have got to be kidding.
So this is a rhetorical, so he's
not talking about joking here.
He's saying, no way, I can't believe it.
This is not happening to me.
- Yeah, you're not serious.
- You're not serious, so he's upset.
And I would be too, no
one likes to be grounded,
but he's saying, okay, come
on, no way, that's too serious.
- That's right, so this is
a phrase that you can use
with someone if you're not
really believing what they're
saying or you're surprised,
you have to be kidding me.
- Yeah, but usually there's
also a degree of anger.
So you're upset at the decision.
For example, I'm watching
the World Cup right now
and there was a foul and I
was very upset because I didn't
think it was a foul and I said,
you have got to be kidding me.
- That's right, okay, so that's exactly
the way that we would use that phrase.
And well, obviously the
mother had made up her mind,
she's very decided and she
said, I don't want to hear it.
- So this is the end of the conversation.
- Okay, this is one
of those phrases that
will just stop anything
you're talking about.
So they're arguing and she says, nope,
I don't want to hear
it, that means no more
excuses, no more
talking, this is the end.
- That's right, I don't want to hear it.
And it's used in many scenarios, right?
Not only for somebody
being angry or grounded,
but also in a meeting,
I don't want to hear it,
that's it, we're doing my idea,
we're going forward with it.
- Oh, be careful because that's
usually what the boss will say.
- That's right.
- It's not the most gentle phrase.
And so you have to be
careful with how you use it,
but if you have authority,
like you're a parent or you're
a boss, you can say, nope,
I don't want to hear it.
I have made my decision.
- That's right.
Okay, so we've taken a
look at a lot of great things.
Why don't we go back,
listen to our dialogue
one last time and
we'll be back in a bit.
(upbeat music)
- Do you know what time it is?
- Um, 10.
- Get in this door, young man.
It's midnight, you are
two hours past curfew.
- I know, but it wasn't my fault.
I told Jennifer, she had to drop me off
before 10, but she wouldn't leave the party.
- I don't care, you are
grounded for life, Mr.
- Mom, that is so unfair.
- You know the rules and you broke them.
No allowance and no TV for a week.
I usually never ground you, but
this time I have to put my foot down.
- What?
- For being a couple of hours
late, you have to be kidding.
- I don't want to hear it.
Now go to your room.
(upbeat music)
- All right, we're back so
obviously we've all been grounded.
What has the longest
you've been grounded for?
- I was a good girl, so maybe a week.
- Really?
- Um, maybe not even.
I never really gotten
trouble as a kid, but but you.
- I think once I was
grounded the entire summer.
- Ooh.
- Yeah, we're out of summer vacation.
I don't remember exactly what I did,
but my dad was pretty
upset with me and he was
really strict, so I got
grounded quite a bit.
- I tend to think that
girls get in trouble less.
I don't know if it's because they're good.
I think probably it's because they're
better at hiding things from their parents.
- Yeah, maybe.
- 'Cause whenever I would come
home, my mother would always
wake up, but she's very,
she doesn't really understand
what time it is, and so I'd
say oh mom, it's 11 o'clock
good night, and maybe like four o'clock
in the morning, and she had no idea.
- So who was the person or the parent
that put their foot down?
Was it your mom or your dad?
- My dad was the serious one.
- Oh really?
- Yeah, it's interesting
because sometimes it's the dad
that's very strict, and the
mom kind of helps you out
and tries to kind of
not get you grounded or
something, but sometimes
it's the other way around.
The mom is really strict and firm, and
the dad's like come on, don't ground him.
They're just having fun.
Well, I think in some families,
the children understand
who is strict and who
is maybe not so strict,
and so they say oh, well
mom said that it's okay,
so I think maybe you should
let me go out and the dad
will be very angry because
the mother said that it's okay.
- That's right.
All right, so that's all the
time we have for today.
We're really curious to get
your stories, maybe tell us
why were you grounded or
how long were you grounded for?
- Or what was your curfew when
you were a child or growing up?
Our website is EnglishPod.com,
we hope to see you there.
- All right, we'll see you guys there, bye.
(upbeat music)